avoiding gluten is a must for people
with celiac disease but a gluten-free
diet can have negative impacts watch the
video to find out why
[Music]
over the last decade or so there's been
a growing interest in the medical
literature on plant-based eating beyond
just exclusionary terms like vegetarian
or vegan
previous such studies were somewhat
limited because they just split people
up into either vegetarian or
non-vegetarian excluding some or all
animal foods but without taking into
account the quality of plant foods
vegans could be living off of french
fries oreos and coca-cola
enter
changes in plant-based diet quality and
total and cause-specific mortality the
first study to investigate the
associations between changes in
plant-based diet quality and subsequent
risk of death
if you look at overall plant-based diet
scores the more you increase your intake
of any plant foods and decrease your
intake of any animal foods the lower
your risk of death appears to fall but
that's because people were adding
healthy plant foods like fruits and
vegetables if you just look at people
who ate more processed sugary junk over
time their mortality risk goes up
the clinical implications being that
increasing intake of healthy plant foods
and decreasing intake of not just animal
foods but also animal crackers
could lower the future risk of premature
death whereas just reducing the intake
of carbs in general cutting down not
just refined carbs and sugars but
healthy high carb foods like fruits and
whole grains is associated with
increased overall mortality
which could correspond to years of your
life being cut short as well as the risk
of dying specifically from heart disease
stroke and cancer
why are whole plant foods so good for us
much of the benefit may be mediated by
our microbiome there are all sorts of
things threatening our good gut bugs
like the over prescription of
antibiotics however the only factor that
has been empirically shown to be
important is a diet low in microbiome
accessible carbohydrates in other words
prebiotics like fiber and resistant
starch only found one place in abundance
whole plant foods
we went from high mac diets to
big mac diets and may be suffering the
consequences
intake of dietary fiber which is the
main source of max in the diet is
negligibly low compared to how we
evolved such a low fiber diet provides
insufficient food for our gut microbes
starving ourselves of all the wonderful
things they produce for us a low fiber
diet is a key driver of microbiome
depletion and this loss is implicated in
the rampant increase of chronic diseases
that now plague the modern world we
evolve getting perhaps a hundred grams
of fiber a day our gut bugs must have
been in heaven
how do you even get close to that and a
cup of fruit may only have about three
grams a cup of vegetables five grams why
so little
because fruits and vegetables are like
80 to 90
water
one has to go to the dryer plant foods
to really scale it up like beans at 15
grams or intact grains like barley over
30 grams per cup but many people are
avoiding common grains these days like
wheat barley and rye due to gluten but
there is a dark side of gluten-free
diets
now if you have a condition like celiac
disease well then you absolutely have to
avoid gluten but if not the downsides
include the potential for nutritional
deficiencies like not getting enough
fiber and toxic compounds for example
the accumulation of heavy metals in
people on gluten-free diets
those following a gluten-free diet had
significantly increased blood mercury
levels more arsenic flowing through
their systems
the arsenic is likely due to increased
rice consumption because rice is a major
ingredient in gluten-free foods but you
can certainly choose other grains like
sorghum that's my favorite rice
substitute and the higher mercury may
just be because people eating
gluten-free diets were tending to eat
more fish for some reason but the reason
that 10 out of 10 of those without
celiac disease or recognized gluten
sensitivity following a gluten-free diet
experienced a pro-inflammatory
gastrointestinal environment is likely
due to starving your microbial self not
getting enough prebiotics not getting
enough fiber because you're avoiding
grains like wheat so whatever diet you
choose for whatever reason make sure
you're getting enough fiber
[Music]
you